Guide to the Nan Doughty Collection
2016 The Regents of the University of Nevada. All rights reserved.
TEST Repository
The Nan Doughty Collection test
1845-1987
TEST Repository
Doughty, Nanelia
MS-00021
26 Linear Feet (67 boxes)
The materials in this collection document the career and family life of artist, author, and educator Nan Doughty, who came to Las Vegas in 1966 to teach in the English department at UNLV. Doughty's family also had roots in early Nevada and Southwest mining towns. Large amounts of correspondence, genealogical and manuscript materials make up the collection, which spans almost 150 years beginning in the mid-nineteenth century. For additional information on this collection, contact the manuscripts librarian.
Acquisition Note
The Doughty Collection was received in multiple accessions. The accessions were T-3 (the William H. Shockley papers), T-59 (the Seymour Kimball Bradford papers), T-172 (the Nanelia Doughty papers) and 87-107. The 87-107 accession was donated after Nan Doughty's death by her sister Marylou S. Williams and consisted of 27 containers.
Access
This collection is open for research with the following restrictions: at the time of donation, Ms. Williams requested the collection be accessible to herself, Charles Adams, Hal Erickson, Jeannette Gustafson and Norma Engberg for a reasonable time. Williams further stipulated that any publication based on her sister's writings or research must acknowledge Nan Doughty by name with prior approval from Williams or her heirs.
Biographical Note
Bertha Nanelia Siegfried[t] Doughty was born June 27, 1907, in Seattle, Washington, to Nanelia Lou-Vee Bradford and Thornwald Adolphe Arthur Siegfriedt. She was the eldest of five children. Her parents divorced in 1924. Nan attended Queen Anne High School in Seattle. She wrote poetry for the school paper, was a member of the Honor Society, Girls Athletic Association, Girls Club, Latin Club and French Club. Active in sports, Nan ran track and played basketball, baseball, and tennis. She graduated from high school June 13, 1923, in a class of 122 girls and 102 boys.
She moved to Johannesburg, California, with her mother when "the Rand district was booming." They resided there for about one year. Nan attended Stanford University in 1925 "when only 500 women were allowed in the student body." While in attendance at Stanford, Nan contributed poems to the Stanford Literary Magazine. She graduated with her B.A. June 16, 1930.
At the age of 15, Nan was encouraged by an aunt, who was a professional artist, to paint. As an adult she was a member of the Northwestern Printmakers. She made wood cuts of the vanishing customs of the Olympic peninsula. These wood cuts attracted the attention of both artists and historians. She won awards for her etchings and had prints hanging in six museums, in addition to two Seattle galleries that carried her prints.
On June 10, 1944, Nan married William Frank Doughty in Seattle, Washington. Her husband, known as "Doc," was in the Naval Reserves. They had no children. The couple divorced January 3, 1957.
After her divorce Nan Doughty returned to school. She received her M. A. in English from Arizona State University at Tempe in 1963. She sought to continue her graduate studies at Stanford University but was denied admission. A letter signed by John Loftis, acting executive head of the English department, dated July 1, 1959, cited departmental policy that "forbids the admission of candidates who are beyond their mid-thirties" as the reason.
She did her doctoral work at the University of California at Riverside. While there, she initiated and taught courses in English as a second language. She began teaching English at the University of Nevada at Las Vegas in September, 1966. Also, during this time she began to do research on her family's activities in early Nevada mining towns. As a freelance writer she wrote about area history and mining for the Nevadan and the Central Nevada Historical Society's publication Central Nevada's Glorious Past. She taught at UNLV until 1972.
Nan Doughty was a member of the national league of American Pen Women, the Central Nevada Historical Society, Northwestern Printmakers and Phi Beta Kappa. She died in Las Vegas on June 29, 1987, at the age of 80. She was survived by two sisters, Victoria S. Barker of Boulder, Colorado, and Marylou S. Williams of Wallingford, Connecticut.
Scope and Contents Note
The chronological scope of the Nan Doughty Collection ranges from 1845-1987. The collection consists of two series. The correspondence series contains letters written by many members of Nan Doughty's family. There is genealogical material to assist with identification of family relationships. The family papers series contains news clippings, school papers, diaries, genealogy records, deeds, stock certificates, manuscript drafts, Desert Research Institute Grant information and notes from UNLV classes. Many of the manuscript drafts are fictional pieces. Much of the material in both series pertains to early mining in Nevada and the Southwest.
For additional information on this collection, contact the manuscripts librarian.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into 2 series:
Series 1. Correspondence
Series 2. Family Papers
Additionally, within each series materials are separated topically into boxes by personal or family names.
Series 1. Correspondence
Series 2. Family Papers
Seperation Note
An extensive photo collection, number 0240, accompanies the manuscript collection. The photo collection consists of over 600 photographs that were originally donated with the manuscript materials in this collection.
Related Materials
Clyde S. Barcus and Edith Giles Collection, MS-00206
Related Materials
Doris Hancock Collection, MS-00282
Related Materials
Mines and Mining Collection, MS-00011
Mineral industries -- Nevada -- History; Mineral industries -- Southwest, New -- History; Women artists -- Washington (State) -- Seattle -- Biography; Women journalists -- Nevada -- Las Vegas -- Biography; Women college teachers -- Nevada -- Las Vegas -- Biography; Doughty, Nanelia; Doughty, Nanelia
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1845-1987; (38 boxes)
  - Introductory Material (Box 01)
  - Correspondence: Ward Family (Box 02)
  - Correspondence to Sallie Jane Leona Ward Wheeler Bradford, (10 boxes) (Box 3-13)
  - Correspondence to Seymour Kimbal Bradford (Box 14)
  - Correspondence to Cora May Wheeler Bradford Schockley, (9 boxes) (Box 15-24)
  - Correspondence to Nanelia Lou-Vee Bradford Siegfried(t), (4 boxes) (Box 25-28)
  - Correspondence to Thorwald Adolph Arthur Siegfried(t) (Box 28)
  - Correspondence to and from Bertha Nanelia Siegfried(t), (5 boxes) (Box 29-34)
  - Correspondence to William Hillman Schockley, (2 boxes) (Box 35-36)
  - Xeroxes, typescripts and indexes of correspondence (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified correspondence (Box 38)
- Series 2. Family Papers, 1845-1987; (28 boxes and 1 oversized folder)
  - Ward Family, 1845-1922 (Box 39)
  - Sallie Jane Leona Ward Wheeler Bradford, 1870-1933; (2 boxes) (Box 40-41)
  - Seymour Kimbal Bradford, 1872-1930s; (7 boxes) (Box 42-48)
  - William Hillman Schockley, 1859-1983; (3 boxes) (Box 49-51)
  - Cora May Wheeler Bradford Schockley, 1895-1986; (3 boxes) (Box 52-54)
  - Siegfried(t) Family, 1901-1974 (Box 55)
  - Bertha Nanelia Siegfried Doughty, 1907-1987; (10 boxes) (Box 56-66)
  - Unidentified material (Box 67)
  - Seymour Kimball Bradford and Sallie Jane Leona Ward Wheeler Bradford, oversized materials (Box OS)